<document xml:lang="nob" id="no_id"><header><title>Stor samling for lakseurfolk i Sápmi til høsten  - Sametinget</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2024</year><wordcount>418</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://sametinget.no/oddasat/stuorra-eamialbmot-luossadeaivvadeapmi-cakcat.32913.aspx?sprak=1</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="stuorra_eamialbmot_luossadeaivvadeapmi_cakcat.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Stor samling for lakseurfolk i Sápmi til høsten</p>
<p><em type="italic">Sametinget i Norge og Samerådet arrangerer 2nd International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples til høsten i Kárášjohka/Karasjok. Lakseurfolk fra den nordlige halvkule samles for å dele kunnskap, erfaringer og for å diskutere urfolks lakseforvaltning. </em></p>
<p>– Laksefisket i Tanavassdraget er stengt den fjerde sommeren på rad. Laksebestanden er under hardt press rundt hele den nordlige halvkule. Vi trenger å møtes for å dele kunnskap og erfaringer med andre urfolk, sier sametingspresident Silje Karine Muotka.</p>
<p>– Lakseelver I Sápmi trues av den nye arten pukkellaks, og denne endringen i elvenes økosystemer virker uunngåelig. Denne samlingen er en utmerket mulighet til å lære fra hverandre om urfolks lakseforvaltningstradisjoner og -kunnskap, men også hvordan nye arter kan benyttes som ressurser, sier Aslak Holmberg, president i Samerådet.</p>
<p>2nd International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples arrangeres på Sametinget i Kárášjohka 30. september – 2. oktober. Dit kommer 80 deltakere fra Sápmi, Canada, USA og Grønland. Denne samlingen er en oppfølging av den første International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples, som ble holdt i Musqueam-folkets områder i Vancouver, Canada i 2022.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In english:</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="eng">Large International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples in Sápmi this fall</p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="italic">The Sámi Parliament in Norway and The Saami Council are organizing the 2nd International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples this autumn in Kárášjohka/Karasjok. Indigenous salmon peoples from the northern hemisphere will gather at the meeting to share knowledge, experiences, and discuss indigenous salmon management. </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">– Salmon fishing has been prohibited in the Deatnu River for four consecutive summers. The salmon population is under severe pressure across the northern hemisphere. We need such a gathering where we can share information and experiences with other Indigenous Peoples, says President of the Sámi Parliament Silje Karine Muotka.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">– Salmon rivers in Sápmi are now facing the arrival of a new species, the pink salmon, and this change of the river ecosystems seems inevitable. This gathering provides an excellent opportunity to learn from each other about Indigenous Peoples’ salmon management practices and knowledge, as well as how to best utilize new species as resources, says Aslak Holmberg, president of The Saami Council.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The 2nd International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples will be held from September 30th to October 2nd in Kárášjohka at the Sámi Parliament. The gathering will host 80 participants from Sápmi, Canada, the USA, and Greenland. This gathering is a follow-up on the first International Gathering of Indigenous Salmon Peoples, which was held on the land of the Musqueam people in Vancouver, Canada in 2022.</p>
</body></document>
